<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Instructions giuen by the princes of Nauarre and of Conde, the Counte of Colligny admyrall of Fraunce, and other lords &amp; gentlemen of their counsell, and others chosen by the nobilitie of the prouinces of this realme, to the deputies of their parte, vpon the conferences holden vvith the sieurs of Biron &amp; Malassize; tvvo of the kings priuie counsell, and deputed by his Maiestie, for the negociation of the peace, most humbly beseeching his Maiestie to graunt vnto them the most iust and necessary demaundes vvhich follovv, for the health of their soules, and preseruation of their honors, lyues, and goodes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108567</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844225</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 547:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Instructions giuen by the princes of Nauarre and of Conde, the Counte of Colligny admyrall of Fraunce, and other lords &amp; gentlemen of their counsell, and others chosen by the nobilitie of the prouinces of this realme, to the deputies of their parte, vpon the conferences holden vvith the sieurs of Biron &amp; Malassize; tvvo of the kings priuie counsell, and deputed by his Maiestie, for the negociation of the peace, most humbly beseeching his Maiestie to graunt vnto them the most iust and necessary demaundes vvhich follovv, for the health of their soules, and preseruation of their honors, lyues, and goodes.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1570]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC; at end: Gyuen at Bussy the. 21. of Iune. anno. 1570.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9016:1"/>
            <head>INSTRVCTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons giuen by the Princes <hi>of Nauarre, and of Conde,</hi> the Counte of Colligny Admyrall of Fraunce, and other Lords &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of their counſell, and others choſen by the Nobilitie of the Prouinces of this Realme, to the Deputies of their parte, vpon the conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces holden with the Sieurs of Biron &amp; Malaſsize, two of the kings priuie Counſell, and deputed by his Maieſtie, for the negociation of the peace, moſt humbly beſeeching his Maieſtie to graunt vnto them the moſt iuſt and neceſſary demaundes which follow, for the health of their ſoules, and preſeruation of their honors, lyues, and goodes.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:9016:2"/>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:9016:2"/>1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat all perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of what qualitie and condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be, and in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer townes and places of thys realme, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the obeyſance and protection of hys Maieſtie they doe dwell or abyde, maye lyue in the ſame in full libertie of conſcience nowe and hereafter wythout impechement or gainſaying, or to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to doe any thing in matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion againſt their will.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That all Gentlemen and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons inhabitants of the realme, or ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, hauing high Iuſtice in all or in part, of their owne in propertie, or during their liues, or elſe ſuch as doe fully poſſeſſe roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties in <hi>Normandy,</hi> may in the ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they haue the ſaide Iuſtice and royalties, and in ſuch places as they ſhall thinke moſt conuenient as well abſent as preſent, haue and cauſe to be vſed the ſaid exerciſe of their religion, as wel for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their houſeholde and tenaunts, as for all other that will reſort thither.</p>
            <p n="3">3 As for other Gentlemen, hauing no
<pb facs="tcp:9016:3"/> ſuch highe Iuſtice: that they may vſe the ſame exerciſe of the religion in their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for themſelues and their houſhold. So as they doe not dwell in the townes, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, or paryſhes of the ſayde Lordes that haue high Iuſtice (ſauing ſuch as be his Maieſties) or elſe with the ſufferaunce or lycence of the ſayde Lordes of highe Iuſtice. Which it may pleaſe his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to order that by his example the ſame licence may not be refuſed. And ſhall not ſuffer them to be reproched or blamed as breakers of his Edict, if there reſort to the ſayd exerciſe of religion any other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s than of their owne houſholde, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if there happen any chriſtning that requireth haſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That in all townes and places where the exerciſe of the ſayde religion is nowe vſed, the ſame may ſo continue. And to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate the reaſt of the Prouinces of this realme with the ſame exerciſe of the religion, that in thrée townes of the ſame Prouinces and gouernments to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the ſayde Edict, the exerciſe of the religion ſhall be vſed for all perſons that will reſort thyther.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That the Quéene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:9016:3"/> Princes and Princeſſes of the bloud, and the principal officers of the crowne, being at the Court, may vſe the ſayde exerciſe of the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lodgings of their traines.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That vnder the name of the exerciſe of the religion may be compriſed all actes appertayning as well to the miniſtery, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, and diſcipline, as alſo to the publike and priuate teaching of children &amp; others.</p>
            <p n="7">7 As for Churchyardes, for the buriall of the deade, that the Lordes of high Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Maiors, Aldermen, and officers of the places where the ſayde exerciſe of the religion ſhall be permitted, may thereof conſider and take order. And in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they ſhall get ſome place to burie the deade, and therein to haue the aſſiſtance of the kings officers.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That in all Vniuerſities and ſchooles, all perſons may be indifferently receiued, whether it be to teach or to ſtudy, and not to be queſtioned withall, or forced for the matter of religion.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That al pore and ſick folkes ſhal alſo be receyued into the Hoſpitals &amp; other like houſes, and haue part of all publike alme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and be vſed with lyke indifferencye,
<pb facs="tcp:9016:4"/> being of the one religion or the other.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That thoſe of the ſayde religion ſhall not be chalenged for their mariages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the degrées not forbidden by the lawes receyued in this realme.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That the lymits of .x. leagues men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the article touching the exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the religion forbidden at <hi>Paris,</hi> as vncertaine, may at the leaſt be chaunged into the Prouoſtie and Viſcontie. In the which if it ſo pleaſe his Maieſtie, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde it abſolutely, he ſhall not néede to be further preſſed, to haue the exerciſe of the religion there. But if that ſhall not pleaſe his Maieſty: yet that it may pleaſe him to moderate ſomewhat the ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this commaundement, and not to take awaye from all Lordes of highe Iuſtice, the generall licence giuen vnto them, to vſe the exerciſe of the ſayde reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſome of them hauing chiefe Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips within the ſayde Prouoſtie and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contie, which ſhall be named vnto him by the ſayde Deputies. This to be done as well on the behalfe and fauour of the ſaid Lordes, as of a great number of people that otherwiſe ſhal be without heauenly &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9016:4"/> ſpiritual foode, or elſe ſhal be to much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in going farre, to haue it farre of, but chiefly for the chriſtning of their children.</p>
            <p n="12">12 And as touching that which (next vnto the conſcience) is moſt déere vnto all perſons, that is, the honor and goodes, and to lay a ſure foundation in that which ſhal be for this cauſe ordred, to the ende there be no doubt made of the ſinceritie of the Quéene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> of the Princes of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and of <hi>Conde,</hi> the father and the ſonne, according to the aſſurance gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to his Maieſtie of their part, that all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hath bene done in theſe warres, was done for a good meaning, and for the zeale of their religion: his ſayde Maieſtie ſhal declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his good Coſins, faythfull ſubiects and ſeruauntes, as in lyke caſe he doth take and eſtéeme the Lordes, Knightes, Gentlemen, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, officers, and other inhabitants of the townes and Boroughs of this realme and countries of his obeyſance, who haue folowed, ſuccoured, and holpen them in the ſaide warres, in what place or ſort ſoeuer the ſame hath bene, to be his good and faithfull ſubiects and ſeruaunts. And
<pb facs="tcp:9016:5"/> for like good and reaſonable occaſion, his Maieſtie ſhall declare that he doth take the heyres of the late Duke of <hi>Deux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pontes,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Orange,</hi> Counte <hi>Ludouic</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> his brother, and <hi>Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi> Counte of <hi>Manſfeld,</hi> to be his good Couſins, neighbors, and friends.</p>
            <p n="13">13 And to ſhew himſelfe to be ſo in déede towards the ſayde perſons: he ſhall order that the ſayde Princes of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and <hi>Conde,</hi> ſhall enioy thoſe lands belonging to them, which haue bene taken from them, and are in the handes of the king of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Or elſe for lack of ſatiſfaction to be made by the ſayde king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the King ſhall giue them letters of Mart.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Alſo his Maieſtie ſhall effectuallye cauſe the ſayde Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and Countie <hi>Ludouic</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> his brother, to be reſtored and put in poſſeſſion, in the principaltie of <hi>Orange,</hi> rightes, landes, and iuriſdictions of the ſame, and all that therevnto belongeth, and alſo in other lands, Lordſhips, and iuriſdictions, which they haue in his realme and obeyſance. Of which principaltie, one parte of the places haue bene taken by the <hi>Sieur</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:9016:5"/> 
               <hi>Suſe</hi> Knight of the order, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places haue bene ſeazed by the kings letters patents for his ſeruice. And that the ſayd Prince and Counte his brother, may from henceforth enioye the ſame, as they did before the troubles, and as it is expreſſed in the treaties of peace, made betwéene the late king Henry of Fraunce and the king of Spaine, and other proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and declarations ſithence graunted for the behoofe of the ſaide Prince: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all procéedings, ſentences and orders, made and giuen during the troubles, which ſhall be as nothing, and of none effect or force.</p>
            <p n="15">15 He ſhall alſo cauſe to be reſtored ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to the ſayd noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, titles and documents, rents, fruits, and reuenues appertayning to them, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the time of the preſent troubles, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in the ſayd principalitie, as in the landes of his maieſtie, the ſame to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the Commiſſioners, at the tyme of the execution of the Edict of pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by ſuch other of the kings officers, as the ſayde noble men will chooſe.</p>
            <p n="16">16 And his Maieſtie meaning to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire
<pb facs="tcp:9016:6"/> all things happened in the tyme of theſe warres, as much as he can: his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie will giue order that al priſoners and ſuch as haue bene ſtayed by iuſtice, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Galleys vpon occaſion of theſe troubles, ſhall be ſet at lybertie on eyther part, without paying any rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſome. And as for the Raunſoms alreadie payde, there ſhall nothing thereof be recouered.</p>
            <p n="17">17 And whereas variaunce may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to aryſe vppon occaſion of ſales of landes and other immouable goods, and engaygings made vpon occaſion of raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Duke of <hi>Aniou</hi> the kings brother, (calling vnto him the Mareſchals of Fraunce) to be by him decyded and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: It may be ordered that all perſons, aſwell of the one Religion as of thother, reciprokely, and whome it toucheth, ſhal enter agayne into all their immouable goodes, which they did poſſeſſe before the ſayde troubles, and that haue fallen vnto them during the ſame. And as for their mouable goodes which ſhall be founde to remayne, the ſame ſhall be reſtored vnto them purely &amp; ſimply: &amp; ſo ſhall alſo ſuch as haue bene taken betwéene neighbours
<pb facs="tcp:9016:6"/> and neighbours, and deliuered in truſt to be kept. And as for ſuche as haue béene ſolde by order of Iuſtice, they ſhall haue them agayne, paying the ſame price that they were ſolde for. And yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſuch as haue béene taken by way of hoſtilitie, ſhall remaine as good priſe, and not to be brought againe in queſtion.</p>
            <p n="18">18 All they alſo of the ſaid religion ſhall recouer all offices of iuſtice, of reuenues and other, togither with the benifices wherevnto they haue any intereſt, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy them wholy and peaceably, and alſo al offices of dignities, gouernements, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainſhips, charges, or penſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which they had before the ſayde troubles, except it be that they were conſtrayned to reſigne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the kinges Edict made in that behalfe. In which caſe they ſhall reſtore the profite which they ſhall haue thereof in déede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, as likewiſe they of the ſayde reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion do offer of their part to be a meanes for the whole reſtitution of their ſayde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and benifices, to reuoke and recouer from them to whom through the neceſſity of the warres, they haue ſolde the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reuenue of the Cleargie, the king
<pb facs="tcp:9016:7"/> graunting vnto them ſuche letters and commiſſions as ſhall be requiſite for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="19">19 That all procéedinges, ſentences, iudgements, and definitiue or interlocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory decrées, giuen againſt anye of them of the religion, of what ſorte or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ſo euer they be, as well deade as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, whether they haue borne armes or not, at the beginning, ſince, and during the troubles, and by occaſion of the ſame, till the day of the ſayde Edict, ſhall be broken, reuoked, and made voyde, and ſo alſo all executions, if there haue béene any, and all markes, tokens, and monuments, of the ſaid ſlaunderous executions againſt their perſons, and the remembraunce of them, taken away with ſuch ſolemnitie as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the full reparation and recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of their honor. And the places where the ſayd executions haue bene made, to be eſtabliſhed in their firſt ſtate, and reſtored to the owners of the ſame. And as for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill procéedings and proceſſes, the parties to be put in their firſt ſtate as they were before the troubles.</p>
            <p n="20">20 All preſcriptions happened during
<pb facs="tcp:9016:7"/> the ſayd troubles ſhall be voide, and taken as though they had not happened, and no meanes left whereby any of eyther reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may helpe themſelues therewith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt other.</p>
            <p n="21">21 And for the better eſtabliſhing of the peace for the tyme to come, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all inequalities, and a like good vſage to be ſhewed equally to all the kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: all thoſe townes that be or haue béene kept by thoſe of the ſayde religion, ſhall be vſed with like equalitie as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be, and not to be grieued and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with lones, garriſons, or anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burthens, and the inhabitauntes of them and of others of this realme being of the religion, or that ſhalbe thereof here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, ſhall be indifferently admitted to all offices, dignities, charges, and publike functions, and called alſo to all counſels and determinations, in towne, houſes, or in generall offices of Prouinces.</p>
            <p n="22">22 That all places, townes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces ſhall remaine and enioy the ſame priuileges, exemptions, lyberties, and franchiſes, which they did before the ſaide troubles.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb facs="tcp:9016:8"/>23 That the king ſhall extend the beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his Edict of pacification (in ſuch ſort as he doth to all his owne ſubiects, and to thoſe that be vnder his obedience and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection) to thoſe that be of the countie of <hi>Veniſſe,</hi> and of the Archbiſhopricke of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uignon,</hi> as being within his realme, and within the compaſſe or circuite of hys crowne, at the leaſt for the reſtitution and enioying of their goodes, the libertie of their conſciences, their ſure habitation and frée acceſſe and trading within hys realme, and within the ſayd Countie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed Archbiſhoprike, as the kings own and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſubiects doe and may doe: And this for the reaſons that haue béene more at large ſet forth to the <hi>Sieurs de Biron</hi> and <hi>de Malaſſize,</hi> &amp; ſpecially for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the kings right and authority in the ſayd Countie and Archbiſhoprike.</p>
            <p n="24">24 That althoughe the Reyters who haue béene called to the ſuccor of thoſe of the religion at their great néede, and who be yet with them, ought to bée payde by ſuch as haue béene the firſt and principall authors of this warre, and that haue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled and in maner conſtrayned the king
<pb facs="tcp:9016:8"/> therevnto, and ſince alſo to continue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, notwithſtanding the earneſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall inſtance made by them of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for the peace, and namely ſince the ioyning with them of the ſayd late Duke of <hi>Deuxponts:</hi> Yet neuertheleſſe for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of theſe contentions, and not to omit one onely poynt of all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them, they of the ſayde religion offer to contribute towards the ſayd pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſumme that the king ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by hys ſaid Commiſſioners. And for the doing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame they offer the firſt part of the reuenue of all thoſe that be of the religion, and that they maye be after that rate taxed and coated according to their vocations and liuing, as it is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed, vntill the ſumme which ſhall be declared, ſhall be perfourmed, deducting onely from the ſame reuenues the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie charges, and forbearing the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion till the next yeare, bicauſe the fruites of this preſent yeare ſhall ſcarcely ſuffice for the entertainment of the ſaid Reyters. And the ſaid taxation or coting to be made vpon them that be of this realme onely.</p>
            <p n="25">25 That all letters of pardon and of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holiſhments
<pb facs="tcp:9016:9"/> graunted by the king, eyther generall or particular, for matter happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before and during the troubles for the cauſe of religion, ſhall haue theyr full force and effect, and ſhall be executed by the Commiſſioners for this Edict of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification.</p>
            <p n="26">26 That the Quéene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and <hi>Conde,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſonne, the Lords, gentlemen, officers and others, that haue ayded and ſuccoured them in their warres, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine quit and diſcharged of all money that hath béene by them, or by their order taken &amp; leuied of the receipts &amp; reuenues of the king, to what ſumme ſoeuer the ſame doth amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto, as alſo of townes commonalties, and of rents, reuenues, &amp; treaſories, of the ſale of moueable goodes, as well of the Church as of others, that are come of the ſale of the kings timber, woodes, alienation of the temporaltie and reuenues of the Church, of forfeytures, bootyes, raunſoms of priſoners, &amp; of any other ſummes of money, of what nature ſoeuer, by them or by their knowledge and conſent taken, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion of theſe wars
<pb facs="tcp:9016:9"/> without any daunger to them and their heyres, or to thoſe that haue bene by them appointed to leuie the ſayde money, or that haue furniſhed and giuen the ſame, to be touched eyther for the preſent time, or the time to come. And as well them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues as their ſayde Deputies ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine diſcharged of the handling, dealing and imploying of the ſame, bringing (for full diſcharge) an acquittance of the ſaide Quéene, or of the ſayde Princes, or of them before whome they were to giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The eſtabliſhment alſo of officers of Iuſtice made by them, of iudgements and executions of the ſame authoriſed and confirmed in time paſt, ſhall ſo remayne. And alſo ſuch as haue bene appointed De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties or Commiſſioners of what ſort ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, ſhall remayne diſcharged of all trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and contracts by them made with all Princes, Potentates, and foraine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalties, of all negotiation with them, of bringing in of the ſayde ſtraungers, of caſting of Ordinaunce, making of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Saltpeter, taking of Ordinaunce and munitions in the kings Storehouſes, and of particular fortifications and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:9016:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9016:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:9016:11"/> of townes, ſpoyling and burning of houſes, of Churches, of leuying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting of men of warre, and of all actes of hoſtilitie, and generally of all that hath bene done and treated before and ſince the preſent warre, and the warres paſt, as though it were particularly expreſſed and ſpecified. And to this ende, that all things done by the knowledge and conſent of the ſayde late Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> or of the ſaid Quéene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and the other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhall be ſufficient for all warrant and diſcharge.</p>
            <p n="27">27 And for as much as in the diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Iuſtice (whereof doth chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the ſuretie of this Edict of pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) diuers abuſes haue bene commytted, which procéeded of the paſſion and partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the moſt part of the Iudges, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe of the religion: therefore to preuent the lyke dealing, and that from one warre there be not an entry made to an other more intollerable for them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of Iuſtice, the proces of thoſe of the religion, both ciuill and criminall, as well on the behalfe of the plaintife as of the defendant, ſhall be treated &amp; heard
<pb facs="tcp:9016:11"/> at the firſt, before the ordinary Iudges, and after, vpon appeale, before certaine others to be taken of all the bodyes of the ſaide Courts of Parliaments, as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall accorde and agrée vpon, to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine number by which according to theſe particuler orders of the ſayde Courtes of Parliament, iudgement may be giuen, ſauing where the parties cannot agrée, within one onely and that a ſhort delaye, then the ſayde proceſſe ſhall be iudge in the high councell, being called therevnto foure mayſters of the requeſtes of the number of thoſe that the king ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt, for the matter that ſhall be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thoſe of the religion.</p>
            <p n="28">28 As for the aſſuraunces, that it hath pleaſed the king of himſelfe voluntarily to graunt vnto them of the religion, not in reſpect of it, but for the conſeruation of himſelfe, vntil the ſharpneſſe of the warre might be qualified with the time, and hath for that ende (for certaine yeares) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them to haue the kéeping of the townes of <hi>Rochel, Montauban,</hi> and <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerre,</hi> and that they may there during and after the ſayde terme, vſe the exerciſe of
<pb facs="tcp:9016:12"/> the ſayde religion: They deſire and moſt humbly beſéeche, that it maye pleaſe the king, for the reaſons that they haue more at large declared vnto the <hi>Sieurs de Biron</hi> &amp; <hi>Malaſſize,</hi> to graunt vnto them <hi>la Charite</hi> in ſtéede of the towne of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerre</hi> for the ſayde aſſurance, and to adde to the number of the thrée townes, the towne of <hi>Angouleſme,</hi> in reſpect of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the ſayde <hi>Rochell,</hi> and for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter health ſake, and other commodities.</p>
            <p n="29">29 Beſide theſe things, and touching others beſides the King, as is aforeſayde, there haue bene diuers other thinges propounded, contayned in the Articles preſented vnto the King, of which there can nor ought to be cut off ſcarcely one, ſeing they ſerue all to this ende, that the peace maye be the ſurer and ſtronger. True it is, that the principalleſt and moſt important of them, are, that all ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, men of warre, maye withdrawe themſelues the ſpéedieſt that maye be out of this Realme, the Kings ſubiectes to their houſes, or other places that they ſhal chooſe for their abode without being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached.</p>
            <p n="30">
               <pb facs="tcp:9016:12"/>30 And to take away all miſtruſting; and not to giue libertie to the gouernors of Countries to execute their reuenge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt townes, and ſpecially againſt thoſe that haue bene or are kept by thoſe of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to cauſe them to redéeme their yll handling by force of exactions vpon the inhabitantes of the ſame Townes: It maye pleaſe the King to diſcharge all thoſe townes that be not vpon the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires, and wherein there haue béene no Garriſons vſed to be put.</p>
            <p n="31">31 That all the Mareſchals of Fraunce in ryding their circuites according to the diſtribution of their prouince, ſhall be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanied with Gentlemen and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men of learning of both the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in lyke number, at the leaſt of the leſſe partiall and moſt louers of peace and common tranquilitie. Which ſhall bée lykewiſe put in vre at the choyſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the Commiſſioners, for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Edict of pacification.</p>
            <p n="32">32 That the ſayde Mareſchalles of Fraunce and Commiſſioners, ſhall cauſe the inhabitantes of the townes of both the Religions to ſweare, the obſeruing and performing of the ſaid Edict in all points
<pb facs="tcp:9016:13"/> And ſhall giue the charge of the one vnto the others, and ſhall charge them reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely and by publike act, to aunſwere for the breach of the ſaid Edict, made by them of their ſayde Religion, within the towne or village where they ſhall dwell, at the leaſt wiſe orderly, or otherwyſe to preſent them to the Iuſtice.</p>
            <p n="33">33 That no perſon ſhall taxe or reproch any other, for any thing paſt during the troubles, and that which toucheth them, eyther by worde or by writing, openly or pryuately, and leaſt of all, in Sermons, or in any publike actes, ſauing in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the deducing of their rightes.</p>
            <p n="34">34 The trade of merchandize ſhall be reſtored and eſtabliſhed in the ſame liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſuretie, as it was wont to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the ſubiectes of his maieſtie, and others, and change of habitation permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to all. And the Princes, ſtraungers, and forreine potentates ſhall be required of his Maieſties parte, to ſuffer lykewiſe the ſaide trafficke, in their countries and landes, without exception of any perſon or religion.</p>
            <p n="35">35 It may pleaſe his Maieſtie to cauſe the exact obſeruation of the ſayde Edict, to
<pb facs="tcp:9016:13"/> be ſworne by the Quéene his mother, the Dukes of <hi>Aniou</hi> and <hi>Alencon</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all the princes of the bloud, Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>challes of Fraunce, and by thoſe of the Kings priuie Counſell, and officers of his Crowne. And that they may gyue Acte of the ſayde othe vnder their ſignes and Seales to thoſe of the ſayde Religion.</p>
            <p n="36">36 That the gouernors of Prouinces, Mayors, Aldermen, heade Officers, and Counſellers of townes, maye make the lyke othe, and renewe it euerie yere.</p>
            <p n="37">37 That all ſentences, and declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ſhall happen to the preiudice of the ſaide Edict, ſhall be voyde and of none effect. Which Edict ſhall be firme, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and irreuocable, and theſe words ſhal be mentioned. In the Preface of the ſaide Edict ſhall be mentioned, all derogations, and notwithſtanding that, and namelye thoſe in the ſaide ordinaunces made vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the alienatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of reuenue and vnitings to the Crowne, and alſo the ſaide deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Edicts, declarations, ſentences, retentions, and ſecret Regiſters made or to be made to ſubmiſſions, voluntarie, or conſtrayned, publike or particular.</p>
            <p n="18">18 That there ſhall be a place and daye
<pb facs="tcp:9016:14"/> of publication, which may not be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or deferred for any occaſion whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Vpon payne that thoſe that make delay ſhall make aunſwere in their owne name. And that ſhalbe without alteration, kéeping backe, or ſecret Regiſter.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Gyuen at Buſſy</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the. 21. of Iune. Anno.</hi> 1570.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9016:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
